[SPEAKER_01]: So, I thought you could, maybe, say something more about jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got some, a section of Majjhima 39, where it talks about jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's part of the, what they call, the anupabha gamma,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's after the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: After having abandoned these five hindrances, defilements of the mind, that weaken understanding, quite secluded from sense desires, secluded from unwholesome things, with thinking, with pondering,
[SPEAKER_01]: He dwells having attained the first jhāna, the joy and pleasure born of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: He drenches, steeps, fills, pervades this very body with the joy and pleasure born of seclusion, so that there isn't any part of the entire body that is unpervaded by the joy and pleasure born of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine, Bhikkhus, a skilled barber, or a barber's apprentice, who, having scattered soap powder onto a dish, would sprinkle it bit by bit with water, so that this lump of soap powder goes moist, becomes moist inside and out, pervaded with moisture and not dripping.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just this way, Bhikkhus, Bhikkhu drenches, steeps... Not too much, not too little.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just the right amount.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that's another thing that people often, like, read over that passage and thinking, almost, when I get jhāna, I get the pleasure of jhāna and then I focus on that pleasure and I sort of pervade my body with that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even those passages says that the pleasure comes from the being secluded from our whole soul.
[SPEAKER_00]: It occurs to me that actually... You dwell because you entered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You dwell in jhāna because you entered it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Accompanied.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with simultaneous pleasure present, which is a direct result of seclusion, not a direct result of the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you say that the first jhāna is that pleasure, that joy and pleasure from... of seclusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is not that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is the clarity of the mind that has surmounted and experienced pleasure on account of surmounting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if anything, that pleasure will come before the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Steadying your mind in that pleasure, because you recognize it's a wholesome pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure, basically, it's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: That pleasure is a good symptom of few healing from sensuality and unwholesome states and the pressure of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: By having come beyond them, by understanding them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: But having gone beyond...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you understand the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understand the relief that arises as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you dwell in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why jhānas are wholesome and often are kind of given as a way of fortifying your understanding of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pervading your body with this pleasure, well, first of all, you need to get that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't get it by attending to your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get it by understanding the extent of centrality and the five hindrances and surmounting that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's an indirect thing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't get pleasure by focusing on sensations in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get pleasure by understanding what is the nature of the hindrances and me being subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the extent of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the necessary basis for hindrances?
[SPEAKER_00]: And maintain the clarity of that context in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get the pleasure as a result of the relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: By realizing that you stepped outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you get to pervade your body with that pleasure that has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by now take this pleasure and pervade it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they'll be like, again, going back to taking things up in the same sense you were taking hindrances up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You pervade it by protecting the same context because of which this pleasure resulted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maintaining the clarity of the domain, recollectedness, and the extent of the body, being clear about the extent of the body, oh, this is how big... and the clearer you become about the extent of the body, head to toe, the clearer it gets pervaded by the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not taking the pleasure and sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Smearing it all over yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I'll move it down to my shoulders.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no, I am doing this, I'm doing that, in the jhāna, because it's it's set up properly and then this has, this establishment is the result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you say, you pervade the body with this joy and pleasure that comes from seclusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: From being secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding that you are secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: You pervade the body with that by becoming clearer and clearer about the phenomenon of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, by providing the body for it to be pervaded by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, by providing the body, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you provide a body by practicing clarity of the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, by the way, about the hindrances, because they're entirely within the body, they're entirely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you not being developed,
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to the extent of the body, you get affected and pressured and burdened and subjected to these hindrances that are entirely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Entirely bound up with the body and cannot occur anywhere else except within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, you know, you could be sleepy, but it's not necessarily a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even even when you're like really really tired and sleepy, it can be a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it really... it's not determined by what's in your body in a sense of whether it's sleepy or excited or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined how much the mind is above it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pervade this body by pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure has a reason on its own as a result of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you want to pervade the body
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning the body even more for what it is, and then the same pleasure will keep arising to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why not too much, not too little, because you can only discern the extent of the body to the extent that it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not discerning the extent of the body correctly means either overdoing it or underdoing, making it too wet or too dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've overcome the hindrances by
[SPEAKER_01]: Being clear about the the basis for the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not being clear in a sense of figuring it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I see is a necessarily present thing right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you're clear about it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is that what we spoke with before, that peripheral notion of recognition of your body here, enduring, as a necessary basis for excitement, for your will, for drowsiness, for worry, for doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: People who think doubt is mental, it is when it's a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it's just... like, why would you then literally perceive it as a as a kind of bodily discomfort, when you're in doubt?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also about... it's on the level of the of the domain of the of the senses and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because doubt can only be about the content of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be about the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And content of things, it's already within the layer of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically, without, you're always looking for...
[SPEAKER_00]: Something passed the senses, some other thing in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having abandoned the five hindrances, having abandoned desire towards the world, any concern regarding the world...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having discerned the body to the necessary extent, as a basis for the entire world, my world, their world, anything in between, it has to be within the basis of this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you just maintain that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the clarity of your seclusion becomes developed, you will experience relief, because you will feel safe, because you're verifying factual safety from concern, from centrality, from the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, as I said, you don't... you can't take that pleasure, because you haven't created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pervade your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: How?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by the same manner how you pervaded in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: By providing the clarity of the extent, pleasure affects it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pervade it by fully clarifying that extent further and further, or simply by repeating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will keep pervading it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, it's the same like in the third or the fourth jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's the fourth jhāna described as a... covered with a white cloth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, to the last... basically, from the highest tip of your head,
[SPEAKER_00]: To the toe, there is not a bit of the body that's not covered, that something else is included, or the body hasn't been included enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like when you outline the extent of the body as a clear context in your mind, to such clarity and refinement, such as imagine if you're completely wrapped in a white cloth, just to the extent that your outlines of your body are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how that pleasure is felt, of that equanimity in the four jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yuri?
[SPEAKER_00]: And again.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I thought we'd go through the similes, then the other jhānas and similes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can read them out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, furthermore, bhikkhus, with the calming of thinking and pondering, with internal clarity, you might say peripheral clarity... Yeah, clarity of the context or the extent... of a unified mind, so with a unified mind, without thinking, without pondering, a bhikkhu dwells having attained the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: The joy and pleasure born of composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now it's not the joy and pleasure of seclusion, but of composure, samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, he drenches, steeps, fills, pervades this very body with the joy and pleasure born of composure, so that there isn't any part of the body that is unpervaded by the joy and happiness born of composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine a lake of spring water for which there were no inflow from the east, from the west, from the north, from the south.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that the lake is, to that extent it's filled with water.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not doing it on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not filling it as much as you want, as much as you desire, or as much as you think you should.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's getting filled to the extent that you discern that it can be filled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like the lake determines how far that cool water is going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only by being clear about what the body is, the extent of the body, can you be clear about the extent of joy and pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's defined by the extent of the body, and that's why there is no craving in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to crave for the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are doing it, that is already rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want it here, I don't want it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's rooted on the level of preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, there's the fading away of the joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: A bhikkhu dwells indifferent, recollected and aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you were saying how it's all based on the collectedness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's now like... it's almost like the recollectedness, the samādhi, the sati.
[SPEAKER_00]: The collectedness is becoming more and more composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stronger and clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: More standing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he dwells indifferent, recollected, aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: He experiences a pleasure with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure with the body, indifference with the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure, indifference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: He drenches, steeps, fills, pervades this very body with the pleasure free from joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there isn't any part of the body that's unpervaded by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, imagine a pond of lilies or lotuses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some were born in the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, some lilies and lotuses that were born in the water have grown up submerged in the water without rising out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the cool water trenches, steeps, fills, pervades their tips and roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that there isn't any part of the entire lily or lotus that is unpervaded with cool water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, just the kind of, I don't tip, tip to the root from head to toe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body is like the lotus that's fully immersed in the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing that hasn't been permeated by the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the last one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having abandoned pleasure, having abandoned pain, with the previous disappearance of happiness and unhappiness, a bhikkhu dwells having attained fourth jhāna, neither pleasure nor pain, clarified by the indifference of recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now the body is neither pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a neutral state, with indifference of the compulsion.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that neither... well, nothing's felt to the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly to the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing felt there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither pleasure, nor displeasure is felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that so?
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't you say that neither pleasure nor pain is a feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if you know neither pleasure nor non-pleasure, it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what not feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know what neither pleasure nor displeasure is, you are affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know it, which means it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, even in case of an arahant, it's not that they discover some super extra dimension in between the feelings, so they don't feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's either pleasure, displeasure or neutral feeling, which is for them all neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they don't feel any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because they know it, that's why it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Sariputra meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact there's nothing felt, that's why it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on one level, it's nothing felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: On another level, that is pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a different type of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, four jhānas, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you were to to develop the four jhāna, it would be impossible to not be another hunt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because four jhāna is not about random
[SPEAKER_00]: magical, pleasurable attainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the amount of clarity there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity about the domain of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity about the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity about the nature of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity about the unshakable, imperturbable context of mindfulness, whatever you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able...
[SPEAKER_01]: Complete equanimity will have to be the result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being skilled in
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, yeah, not, not feeling or like, like, like being unmoved by pleasant feeling or pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, not as a matter of choice, but as a matter of development.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you want to be moved, it would be impossible to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, that's the simile that you...
[SPEAKER_01]: The white cloth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've already said the white cloth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, exactly to the extent...
[SPEAKER_01]: He says...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's funny, he says he's sitting down.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's sitting down, having pervaded this very body with a purified, clarified mind, so that there isn't any part of the body...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: The pervading isn't with a pleasure or joy or anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pervading with a purified, clarified mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that case, you're not anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in another, it's still the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent of the body gets pervaded by the clarity of the mind, which is now that perfect equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're pervading the extent of the body, from the tip of the head to the feet, by that pleasurable equanimity, pleasurable indifference, so to speak, of the completely unpolluted, fully developed compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'd like to answer that context, that kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: What has started indirectly, so to speak, you know, when you're pulled by hindrances, you need to keep discerning the background of the necessary basis for the hindrances, and then you get to approve them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now, going back to the level where the hindrances are, that's now indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind got so established upon that peripheral, as the necessary base, as the, like, really what's first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that order cannot be perverted now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody can develop the mind to the extent of the four jhāna, it's virtually impossible to not be an ārahant then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there will be nothing left.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will not be included in the clarity of the right order, right context, nibbata, mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all, any, all and any basis of passion, aversion and distraction are completely, sort of, evaporated.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even without going all the way to four jhānas, it's the same principle and it's useful, I think, for people, because, you know, everybody likes the idea of jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing wrong with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to understand that the pleasure has nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you have a pleasure of your meditation, and if you can attend to it directly, that's not the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pleasure of some novelty, of some sort of release or whatever you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what everyone is going to experience when they first start meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start calming down, you're going to have, like, as I said, like a novelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow!
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that, see, you can relate to it directly, means it's not the result of your withdrawal from anything you can relate to directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pleasure of the jhāna is... well, first of all, it's not pleasure of jhāna, it's pleasure of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have absolutely no idea what seclusion from centrality and five hindrances is, you can be safe, then, to assume that whatever pleasure you feel in your meditation is not the pleasure you should be pursuing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it comes, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it goes, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't think there's anything special about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't think it's about cultivating that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That should be your job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not even about cultivating the wholesome pleasure of the withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just using it as a symptom to, like, pervade that withdrawal further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, really, it's funny talking about it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body seems to be, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's developing your mind in regard to the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's actually... that's exactly the reason why even an ārya is not an anāgāmī yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: He is not developed to the... How did the sutra put it?
[SPEAKER_00]: His mind is not developed in regard to the body, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it's said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or he hasn't been developed in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sensuality still arises for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either the two types.
[SPEAKER_00]: He hasn't been developed in regard to the body and he hasn't been developed in regard to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he still has work to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have been developed in regard to the extent of your own body, regardless of the occasion, you have basically developed in regard to the extent of the hindrances, which means you cannot be hindered by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what they hinder, you're outside of it now, as in you have surmounted it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not surmounting it, their hindering hinders you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get hindered by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of the hindrances are also fetters, aren't they?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, but that's how it's different, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking, if... You're constantly hindered by something, then you end up developing a view over it, and that's when it's a fetter, like a fetter of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, yeah, okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can free yourself from a fetter of doubt, as in understand the nature of doubt, but still be affected by doubt on a bodily level, in terms of basically feeling, craving in regard to the unpleasant feeling of doubting something.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you've developed jhāna,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, even that cannot touch you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why arahant is the destroyer of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether he's in jhāna or not, those things cannot hinder him anymore, because his mind has developed above.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even at its lowest level, it's still above.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even at its least composed level, least recollected level, it's still above the five hindrances, which is exactly what what makes you an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like when these fetters fall off, they cannot reappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you can't go below that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, peripheral awareness of the body is the starting point of the body that's enduring while you're talking, sitting, being silent, eating, going to the toilet.
[SPEAKER_00]: The image of the body that is there is your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, actually, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Starting point is sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the image of the body... and you're sort of getting at that via hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the beginning?
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having to endure hindrances as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, this sort of indirect pleasure that comes as a sort of... as you realize you're free from that, that then becomes the... the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not just you're free from that, but you realize it by... say, by establishing, by recollecting the extent of the body correctly, and then maintaining that recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You immediately imply not just freedom from these hindrances, but freedom from the future hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole domain, the possible things that could happen, none of it can apply and that is felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's such a tremendous relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's something you need to, like, fabricate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to maintain the context that relief will have to come up with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you can know, yes, you can't have a... you can have a relief without the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't have a jhāna without a relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not because jhāna is the relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is after the relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you get the relief, you get the pleasure, then you still keep doing the same thing, maintaining the same context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you kind of become established upon it, so to speak, where it's not flimsy, where it doesn't go away as soon as you sort of... something pops up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said steady your mind in this practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Steady your mind in the theme of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can do that even before jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, he dwells.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you steady your mind, then you actually dwell in that steadied mind of the relief from everything unwholesome and concerns about the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you dwell in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reality could just be living.
[SPEAKER_00]: He lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: He lives in that state.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say state, I mean that establishment, not like some sort of oblivious, oblivion.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: He lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha says, whether he walks, talks, goes to toilet, eats, he's in... whatever he does is divine because he's in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practicing the recollectiveness of the extent of your body, or, say, mindfulness of the bodily postures, regardless of what hindrance is there...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which means, you're not acting out of hindrance, and you're then maintaining the context, despite the pressure of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you go beyond the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, sometimes it will be more pleasurable, sometimes it will be less, depending on how many hindrances you have arising, how often.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that depends on you, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much you've been giving in to them before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the less you act out of them, the less you give in to them, the less you try to get rid of them, the less you try to indulge them, the less they will arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, then, your pleasure of jhāna will be more and more agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your practice of jhāna will be more and more agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're, if you're, if you are acting out of the hindrance, you're basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to act out of hindrance, I know what you... yeah, the only way you act out of hindrance is to lose the extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, because you're, you're, you're putting yourself first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I, I, I can control...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you catch yourself acting out of hindrance, it's not like, oh, I...
[SPEAKER_00]: Next time I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you want to do is, when you catch yourself acting out of hindrance, now include all of that in the extent of the body, and that's how next time you will not act as much, at least, out of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until it becomes possible to realize, actually, it's not me who is in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, until the clarity becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, hey, wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I attend to this or not, it always remains bound with the body, that's fully understood, and it cannot pertain to me, even if I wanted to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was only by not understanding that it cannot pertain to me, as in to my mind, to me, to my point of view, to my desires, that's how it pertained to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, develop yourself in regard to the body, and sensuality cannot pertain to the mind anymore.